<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Burgeon Lab - Where Projects Prosper</title><link>https://www.burgeonlab.com/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Burgeon Lab - Where Projects Prosper</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-GB</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 19:05:34 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.burgeonlab.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Sudden Influx of New Gear</title><link>https://www.burgeonlab.com/posts/sudden-influx-of-new-gear/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 19:05:34 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.burgeonlab.com/posts/sudden-influx-of-new-gear/</guid><description>&lt;p>Having gone on a deep dive in the mid of September learning about Hugo and Git for documenting my Raspberry Pi 4B homelab journey; I found myself suddenly distracted by a great deal on a Mac Mini M1 in the local second-hand market.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="retiring-my-trusty-daily-driver">Retiring My Trusty Daily Driver&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My digital life, since 2012, has been lived through the Apple MacBook Air mid-2012 13&amp;quot;, maxed out spec (Dual-Core Intel Core i7 2Ghz, 8GB DDR3 RAM, 512GB SATA SSD). It has served me very well over the years, but increasingly more apps are dropping their software support for Catalina, like Adobe Lightroom Classic - an essential app for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also had the internal SSD fail on me last year. Luckily a full format, fsck and clean OS install to Catalina saved it; albeit temporarily. Since then, I&amp;rsquo;ve been on the lookout for a replacement - to which I chose the Mac Mini M1, acting as a stopgap upgrade before investing in a MacBook Pro 14&amp;quot; or 16&amp;quot; with the rumoured impressive 3nm Apple Silicon chip.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Fast forward to last week, I found an almost like new (SSD lifespan only about 1TB data written, less than 30 hours power on hours) Mac Mini M1 in the configuration I want, 16GB RAM + 1TB SSD, for ~$570USD / $540EUR. I pounced at the deal - it even had Apple Care till February of next year!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="apple-m1-misery">Apple M1 Misery?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I always had a smooth experience with macOS El Capitan and Mojave on my Air. Even during the bigger jump to Catalina, most software ran well with no crashes or major issues. All the apps I want to run works well. Unfortunately, I cannot say the same for the M1 Mac Mini running Ventura 13.6.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ventura OS itself was fairly buggy. Even when moving around Finder and System Settings, I found little bugs here and there. These were some of the things that didn&amp;rsquo;t work for me:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Pointer often changes to an &amp;ldquo;adjust width&amp;rdquo; icon even when I&amp;rsquo;m no where near the edge of a window&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The window asking for my password doesn&amp;rsquo;t pop to the front of the Settings window when I change a setting, making it appear as if Settings is not responding&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Universal Control is not straight forward to setup&lt;/li>
&lt;li>USB-A ports on the back loses power/connectivity after sleeping occasionally (Reports of it &lt;a href="https://discussions.apple.com/thread/253514345?answerId=256577222022#256577222022">here&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://forums.macrumors.com/threads/mac-mini-m1-usb-ports-not-working-after-wake-from-sleep.2326616/?post=32549313#post-32549313">here&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Often unable to eject external drives and have to resort to logging out or restarting, even with spotlight indexing turned of for said drive&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Not entering sleep mode normally, constantly has wakeup power events scheduled automatically and repeatedly, which I am guessing is related to the loss of power in the USB-A ports. (Reports of it &lt;a href="https://discussions.apple.com/thread/254333766?page=4">here&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://forums.macrumors.com/threads/macos-ventura-13-1-power-events-cause-wakeup-from-sleep.2373692/">here&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="hardware-fail-there-may-be-an-issue-with-a-memory-module">Hardware Fail: &amp;ldquo;There may be an issue with a memory module.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>After about two days of setting up and manually migrating files over, the Mac Mini started acting really weird with around 50+ logged crash reports in Console, especially with Electron apps. Then Firefox started crashing repeatedly and on came reboot loops with the &amp;ldquo;pink screen of death&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This was it I thought, I bought a second-hand dud. Something must be wrong hardware-wise. I went ahead with an Apple Diagnostic scan &lt;em>(long press power button to enter recovery mode and then press and hold cmd+D)&lt;/em> and lo and behold; there was a memory failure (reference code: PPM001).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.burgeonlab.com/images/memfail_m1.webp" alt="Mac Mini M1 Diagnostic Scan">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I felt silly for not doing this hardware test earlier, before I started setting up all my apps and preferences, troubleshooting through all the weird quirks of Apple Silicon. I brought the Mini straight to the Genius Bar where they said the logic board along with the I/O wall will need to be replaced and will take at least five to seven days.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="cant-retire-yet">Can&amp;rsquo;t Retire Yet&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>So today, I am back writing this post on my trusty MacBook Air. My original plan, after getting the Mini all setup, was to replace the battery and SSD on the Air so it could get a new lease of life. I could test out some linux distros on it, maybe try running Docker, or dedicate it for some side project/experimentation&amp;hellip; I think these might have to wait a bit until I get the Mini running smoothly as my daily driver.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have already bought a nice set of screwdriver bits containing the the Pentalobe 0.8 and 1.2, thermal paste (Arctic MX-4) and a specific SATA M.2 SSD adapter to do the upgrades soon. I will purchase a replacement battery and a SSD nearer the date of upgrade. I&amp;rsquo;m currently considering these SATA M.2 drives:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Micron 1300 1TB&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Micron M600 512GB&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Crucial MX500 1TB&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Samsung PM871 512GB&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I will share which SSD I end up choosing and how to the upgrades go. But to check out the new screwdriver, I took off the bottom cover of the MacBook Air and cleaned out &lt;em>11-year-old dust&lt;/em>! It runs around 5 to 10 °C lower now compared to before cleaning it. I&amp;rsquo;ll replace the thermal paste when I do the memory / battery upgrade. I can&amp;rsquo;t risk losing my daily driver!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.burgeonlab.com/images/dust_before.webp" alt="11 year old crud">
&lt;img src="https://www.burgeonlab.com/images/dust_after.webp" alt="After cleaning my 2012 MacBook Air">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="new-raspberry-pi-5">New Raspberry Pi 5&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Just as I was going to upload this post, I found out the new Pi 5 is coming next month. It is such a bummer that I got mine literally two weeks ago. It is even at the same price but the speed of almost everything is many times faster, not to mention, it has a PCIe slot. Oh well&amp;hellip; I already bought a dual fan attachment, which has arrived earlier this week.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.burgeonlab.com/images/rpi_dual_fan.webp" alt="A dual fan attachment for the Raspberry Pi 4B">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I decided the distro to install is &lt;a href="https://dietpi.com/">DietPi&lt;/a>. Will be seeing if I can boot it from an external SSD (Samsung 870 EVO 512GB SATA SSD) in a USB UGREEN enclosure and start my homelabbing journey!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Hello, Hugo</title><link>https://www.burgeonlab.com/posts/hello-hugo/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 20:08:15 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.burgeonlab.com/posts/hello-hugo/</guid><description>&lt;p>Having grown up with Xanga, LiveJournal, Wordpress.com and Tumblr, then graduating to self-hosting Wordpress; using Hugo is a breath of fresh air in my blogging journey.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="learning-new-things">Learning new things&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In late 2023, I have been trying to wrap my head around GitHub and being more competent with CLI. At the same time, I learnt to customize the macOS terminal with &lt;a href="https://ohmyz.sh/">OMZ&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/romkatv/powerlevel10k">PowerLevel10k&lt;/a>, using nano to edit files, using &lt;a href="https://www.ssh.com/academy/ssh">SSH&lt;/a> with keys and &lt;a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/how-to-use-rsync-to-sync-local-and-remote-directories">rsync&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="my-current-setup">My current setup&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>MacBook Air 13&amp;quot; (mid-2012) 2GHz Dual-Core i7, 8GB DDR3, 512GB running Catalina (10.15) in clamshell mode &lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>OWLab Spring keyboard (my first Alice layout) with KTT Wine Red Linear Switches (44g actuation, 50g bottom out)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>BenQ Zowie EC1-B mouse&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dell 24&amp;quot; U2415 60Hz display&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Coming from someone without any coding background, I have to admit some of what I am learning are hard to grasp. But being a lifetime learner I am determined to get my projects executed!&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="experimentation-with-linux">Experimentation with Linux&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>My motivation to learn these new skills comes from the fact I want to setup a &lt;strong>homelab&lt;/strong> with a Raspberry Pi 4B 8GB rev 9 (which I have &lt;em>finally&lt;/em> acquired at retail price after the restock surge in Q3/Q4 2023).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During the time I was waiting for the restock, I have been messing around with Linux on two old PCs from the early 2010s; a HP Slimline desktop with stock Debian 12 bookworm and a HP Mini 210-1100 netbook with the super lightweight Debian-based distro — &lt;a href="https://antixlinux.com/">antiX&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I learnt how to use Gparted, configure basic network configs and how window managers worked. In the end, I was able to successfully self-host Navidrome and it was exhilarating to say the least!&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="raspberry-pi">Raspberry Pi&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>During this new-found fascination with Linux, I unboxed a brand new &lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.com/news/model-b-now-ships-with-512mb-of-ram/">Raspberry Pi Model B Rev 2 (512MB ram)&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> I bought 11 years ago in 2012! I found it earlier this month while unpacking old moving boxes I have in storage. It is running headless with the latest Raspberry Pi Lite in 32-bit. I installed Pi-Hole, feeling quite pleased with how it turned out! It is indeed a great first project for those starting out with the Raspberry Pi. The guides online were plentiful and relatively straightforward. SSH connection is via my MacBook Air or iPad Mini 6 with &lt;a href="https://secureshellfish.app/">Secure ShellFish&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="creating-a-place-to-log-my-technical-trek">Creating a place to log my &amp;ldquo;technical trek&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2>
&lt;h2 id="choosing-a-static-site-generator-as-my-content-management-system-cms">Choosing a Static Site Generator as my Content Management System (CMS)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Having some experience with &lt;a href="https://www.markdownguide.org/cheat-sheet/">Markdown&lt;/a> while using &lt;a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian&lt;/a> (my choice of PKM which I highly recommend) and back in my college days with &lt;a href="https://apps.apple.com/al/app/mou-markdown-editor/id1308265497">Mou&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://brettterpstra.com/projects/nvalt/">Nvalt&lt;/a> for note taking — I think it is only wise to write in .md for this second blog I&amp;rsquo;m starting. (You can find me under my main handle &lt;a href="https://www.eclecticpassions.net">@eclecticpassions&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Writing in the Wordpress web interface is quite finicky&amp;hellip; I am not a fan. Trying to optimize the webpage load times is also a hassle. Recently, I discovered webrings dedicated to lightweight webpages, e.g. &lt;a href="https://250kb.club">250kb.club&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://512kb.club">512kb.club&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://1mb.club">1mb.club&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These fast, content-focused blogs piqued my interests greatly. I realized most of the sites listed are static websites, using SSGs like Jekyll or Hugo. I also recall some of my Mastodon friends have mentioned it before. Hence, I bought a new domain name on &lt;a href="https://porkbun.com/">Porkbun&lt;/a> (first time customer, liking it so far), installed &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo&lt;/a> (seems to be quite popular and one of the fastest SSGs around), chose a theme (&lt;a href="https://github.com/lxndrblz/anatole">Anatole&lt;/a>) and deployed it with &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="choice-of-domain-name">Choice of domain name&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It took me a day to think of a suitable name but I am quite happy with it. I think &amp;ldquo;Burgeon Lab&amp;rdquo; suits my use case quite well.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Burgeon (&lt;em>verb&lt;/em>) — Begin to grow or increase rapidly; flourish.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I will treat it as a place where I can document my side projects and share my progress.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="setting-up-github-actions">Setting up GitHub Actions&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Being able to run a local instance of my Hugo site was relatively straightforward, but I had quite a bit of troubleshooting headaches before I got the Hugo directory working on my GitHub Pages repo. Will post a tutorial on it soon.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="first-two-projects">First two projects&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To start off, I will be documenting these two topics:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Setting up and using Hugo as a beginner coming from Wordpress&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Setting up self-hosted services on my Raspberry Pi 4B with &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/get-started/">Docker&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.portainer.io/">Portainer&lt;/a>, acting as my first ever homelab server&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Thanks for reading, if you intend to follow along, please feel free to follow my RSS feed or follow me on &lt;a href="https://fosstodon.org/@eclecticpassions">Mastodon&lt;/a> where I will be post updates.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>My beloved MBA from 2012 is still running strong! I am just waiting for the 3nm Apple silicon chips to be released, planning to get either the 14&amp;quot; or 16&amp;quot; MacBook Pro. But with possible rumours of it being delayed, I am considering getting a M1 or M2 Mac Mini with 16GB ram in the meantime (if I can find one in the second-hand market).&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>